Chris: What is creative problem
solving and what does it consist of?
Possibly the most important skill in creative
problem solving is to be open minded and think
outside of the box as the most obvious reason
for something is not always the solution.
Leah: A creative thinker will look at the
situation from all angles and not just jump to
conclusion or go for the most logical solution,
following the path that has always been followed.
They will ask many questions such as ‘why?’ and
‘why not?’ They will look underneath the surface of
a problem and get to the root cause of the issue.
Chris: Once a situation has been thoroughly
explored, the creative thinker will need the
skills to decide on the best course of action.
To do this they’ll need to collaborate with others,
share their ideas and brainstorm the best solutions.
However, unstructured thinking may need to move
to a more structured approach, when looking at how
the solution will be systematically implemented.
A creative thinker needs to use a
range of different skills such as
• Leah: Attention to detail
• Good Communication skills
• Intuitive thinking
• Systematic thinking and Logical approach
• Looking at things differently, from a fresh
perspective and finding new ways to solve a problem
• Innovative thinking
• Questioning approach
• Techniques such as brainstorming, drawing
mind maps and rich pictures, and role-play
• And always keeping an open mind
Chris: as well as these soft skills there are key methods
and techniques that can be considered as a framework.
Anyone can follow these, and they help to ensure
that all the elements of an issue are considered,
whether it be for a new system, locating an error
or solving a problem such as a customer complaint.
Leah: Identify problem- It’s critical to ensure that
you understand exactly what the problem is and not just
rely on information from others as to what they think.
This might take some time investigating but this is
better than wasting time solving the wrong problem
only to find that the original one still exists.
Chris: Clarify problem- To ensure that
your ideas are valid, do your research.
What are other organisations doing, is
there any data to back up your thinking?
This should help you to visualise your
ideas more clearly and enable you to sketch
out a draft of how it will be approached.
Leah: Use Analytics- The research data that you
gather will help you to see patterns, based on what
users, competitors and industry bodies are reporting.
This is particularly useful for new ideas and will
you to understand what might be successful, or not.
Chris: Use Feedback- These steps will provide you
with enough information to present your ideas to
others, an important step that shouldn’t be ignored.
Gaining feedback from colleagues, customers
and other stakeholders can ensure that
you’ve not overlooked any essential elements.
Leah: Solve the problem- After all that groundwork is done
you can now finally begin putting your ideas into practice.
To do this you need to be methodical and not
rush to the end or get distracted along the way.
Remember to keep the ‘ecosystem’ in mind and do not worry
so much about the finer details and design at this stage.
You could use ‘Low-fidelity wireframes’ that
outline blueprints for the project layout.
Paper drawn sketches are excellent for this as with
the ecosystem, don’t get bogged down in the detail and
remember if something’s not working out, to keep an
open mind and explore alternative tools and approaches.
Chris: And finally, if you get stuck don’t forget go
back to your feedback and listen to comments from your
colleagues and other stakeholders, remember talking
through an issue can help unblock creative thinking.